Guide to the John S. Chipman Papers, 1948-2014 and undated RL.11495
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1950-2011; 2
  - Articles, papers, and essays, 1
    - Notes on dynamic stability of the Marshallian model of international trade, undated (Box 6)
    - Notes on the estimation of distributed lags, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Notes on Ethier's "allocation curve" still further revised and expanded, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Notes on Graham's paradox, 2000 (Box 6)
    - Notes on hypothesis testing, undated (Box 6)
    - Notes on international trade under external economies of scale, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Notes on interpolation by cubic splines, 1982; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Drafts, background articles
    - Notes on the characterization of quasi-homothetic preferences, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the duality between production and cost functions: a differentiable approach, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the Heckschur-Ohlin theorem, 2002 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of the cost-of-living index, 1998, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of exchange control, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of exhaustible research, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of fishery resources, 2002 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of public goods, 2002, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of quotas, 1998-2006 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of tariff wars, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Notes on the theory of tariffs, 2000, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Notes on trade-demand functions with two produced tradeables, 2001 (Box 7)
    - On least squares with insufficient observations, 1964 (Box 7)
    - On the concept of international competitiveness, 1989-1992; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Correspondence with Peter Kenen, drafts
    - On the equation of international demand: introductory note, 1975 (Box 7)
    - On the fitting of distributed lags by spline functions in multivariate regression, with a mean-square-error test, undated (Box 7)
    - On the representation and aggregation of homothetic preferences, 1979 (Box 7)
    - On the theory of exchange control, 1992 (Box 7)
    - On the use of idempotent matrices in the treatment of linear restrictions in regression analysis, undated (Box 7)
    - On social welfare functions and the aggregation of preferences, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Optimal aggregation by threhold accepting: an application to the German Industrial Classification System, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Optimal aggregation in large-scale econometric models, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Optimal aggregation of linear time series models, 2004 (Box 7)
      Photocopy
    - Optimal industrial classification, 1994-2004 (Box 7)
      Draft, photocopy, reprint
    - Optimal industrial classification by threshold accepting, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Optimal industrial classification in a model of international transmission of price changes, undated (Box 7)
    - Optimal industrial classification with heteroskedasticity correction, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Ordering of portfolios in terms of mean and variance, 1971 (Box 7)
    - The Paretian heritage, 1973-1976; 3 folders (Box 7)
      Lecture reprint, drafts, correspondence
    - Pareto and contemporary economic theory, 2006 and undated (Box 7)
    - The payoff of investment in CGE modelling, 1991 (Box 7)
    - The problem of testing for serial correlation in regression analysis: the story of a dilemma, 1965 and undated (Box 7)
    - The process of structural adjustment in an open economy: an economic study of Swedish experience since 1971, 1985 (Box 7)
      Application for grant
    - Product diversification, equalization of factor rentals, and consumer preferences, 1985 and undated (Box 7)
    - Projections, generalized inverses, and quadratic forms, 1964 (Box 7)
    - "Proofs" and proofs of the Eckart-Young theorem, 1994-1997; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Protection and exchange rates in a small/open economy, 2000-2007 (Box 7)
    - The rate of growth and the internal rate of return, undated (Box 7)
      Manuscript abstract
    - Real national income with homothetic preferences and a fixed distribution of income, 1980 (Box 7)
    - A reconsideration of the "elasticity approach" to balance-of-payments adjustment problems, 1977, 2007; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Relative prices, capital movements, and sectoral technical change: theory and an empirical test, 1983 (Box 7)
    - A renewal model of economic growth: the continuous case, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - A renewal model of economic growth: the discrete case, undated (Box 7)
    - Request for advanced computing resources at NSF Supercomputer Centers, undated (Box 7)
    - Returns to scale and substitution, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Returns to scale in the railroad industry: a reinterpretation of Klein's data, undated (Box 7)
    - Robustness of least squares estimation of linear trend when residuals are autocorrelated, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Schlettwein's Prize essay, 2003 (Box 7)
    - The scope of consumer's surplus arguments, undated (Box 7)
    - Sex differentials in periodic retirement benefits: a background analysis, undated (Box 7)
    - Slutsky's 1915 article: How it came to be found and interpreted, 2002; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Drafts, reprint, page proofs, correspondence
    - Slutsky's praxeology and his critique of Bohm-Bawerk, 2003 (Box 7)
      Reprint, proofs
    - Social utility and the gains from trade, 1972 (Box 7)
      Reprint, draft
    - Some papers of Pareto from the French and German, 2009 (Box 7)
      Edited by Chipman; Offprint
    - Specification problems in regression analysis, undated (Box 7)
    - Stability, 2008 (Box 7)
    - Statistical problems arising in the theory of aggregation, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Stochastic choice and subjective probability, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
    - The Stolper-Samuelson theorem and the problem of aggregation, undated (Box 7)
    - A survey of the theory of international trade, 1965 (Box 7)
    - Testing for the differences of two means, and for differences in several pairs of means, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Testing for reduction of mean-square error by aggregation, 1985 (Box 8)
    - The theory and application of trade utility functions, 1979 (Box 8)
    - The theory and measurement of income distribution, 1985 (Box 8)
    - The theory of exploitative trade and investment policies: a reformulation and synthesis, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      Draft, reprints
    - The theory of international capital transfers, undated (Box 8)
    - Three aspects of general equilibrium and welfare in the international trade, 2007 (Box 8)
    - A three-commodity model of tariffs, and the dynamics of protectionism, 2003 (Box 8)
    - Towards the construction of an optimal aggregative model of international trade: West Germany, 1963-1975, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Trade balance and exchange rates, 1989 and undated (Box 8)
    - Trade restrictions versus foreign aid as a means of improving a country's welfare, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 8)
      Drafts, correspondence. Re: Higgins Festschrift.
    - The Trade-Slutsky correspondence in a simple Ricardian model, 2004 (Box 8)
    - The transfer problem once again, 1974 (Box 8)
    - The treatment of linear restrictions in regression analysis, 1964 (Box 8)
    - A two-period model of international trade and payments, 1984-1990 (Box 8)
    - Underestimation of sampling variances in least-squares regression when residuals are autocorrected, undated (Box 8)
    - Utility theory in retrospect, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Want list of rare and out-of-print books, 2003 (Box 8)
    - The welfare effect of an excise tax and its overestimation by consumer's surplus, 2005 (Box 8)
    - The welfare ranking of Pareto distributions, 1974 (Box 8)
    - When in a fixed income distribution optimal?, 1985 (Box 8)
      Draft. Re: Arrow Festschrift.
    - Why an increase in GNP need not imply an improvement in potential welfare, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Reviews by Chipman, 1954-1987 (Box 8)
      Various essays.
    - Reviews by Chipman, 1955-2014 (Box 11)
  - Books, 2
    - Essays in honor of Leonid Hurwicz, Volume A, undated (Box 8)
      Drafts (large binder)
    - Hurwicz Volume D: Rejected papers, undated (Box 8)
    - Preferences, Uncertainty, and Optimality: Essays in Honor of Leonid Hurwicz, 1990 (Box 8, 9)
      Published volume, publisher's correspondence
    - Pareto's Collected Papers book, edited by Chipman, 1960s-2010; 6 folders (Box 8)
      Includes drafts, publishers' correspondence, and articles re: Pareto and translations by Chipman and others.
    - Advanced Econometric Theory, 2011; 5 folders (Box 8)
      Published volume, chapter drafts
    - The Theory of International Trade (vols. 1 and 2), 2008-2009; 2 Volumes (Box 9)
    - Estimation and aggregation in econometrics, 1974; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Recursive models, chapter 5: Conditional means (Box 9)
      Draft, book title uncertain
    - Minnesota symposium: Frisch chapter, 1967 (Box 9)
    - Inventory control, undated (Box 9)
      Notes for book chapter, title uncertain
    - A theory of mercantilism (chapter 1), undated (Box 9)
      Chapter draft for book, title uncertain
- Engagements, 1950s-2011; 3
  - Courses and classes taught by Chipman, 3
    - Econ 201B: Econometrics, undated; 5 folders (Box 9)
      Lecture notes, etc.
    - Econ 223A: Growth, 1969 and undated (Box 9)
      Lecture notes, exercises, reading list
    - Econ 224: Factor Price Equalization, 1966; 3 folders (Box 9)
      Lecture notes
    - Econ 254C, 1963; 3 folders (Box 9)
      Notes on combinatorial topology, relational algebra
    - Econ 3103: Welfare Economics, 1996-1999 (Box 9)
    - Econ 4960: Welfare Economics, 2000s (Box 9)
    - Econ 5231: Introduction to Econometrics, 1988; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Econ 5431: International Economics, 1977 (Box 9)
    - Econ 8103: Microeconomic Theory, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Econ 8121: Applied Welfare Economics, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Econ 8211: Econometrics, 1970-1977; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Econ 8212: Econometrics B, 1970-1972 (Box 9)
    - Econ 8401/5461: International Trade, 1973-1990 (Box 9)
    - Econ 8402: International Trade and Payments, 1989-2006 (Box 9)
    - Dehli workshop: short course, undated (Box 9)
    - Lectures in econometric theory 2, undated (Box 9)
    - Welfare economics of excise taxes, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Organizations, Conferences, and Events, 4
    - Air Force Behavioral Sciences Conference, 1957 (Box 10)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1997 (Box 10)
    - American Economics Association Committee on Honors and Awards, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - American Economics Association distinguished fellow, 1999 (Box 10)
    - American Enterprise Institute tribute to Haberler, 1995 (Box 10)
    - American Philosophical Society, 2000-2011; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - American Statistical Association, 1974-1992 (Box 10)
    - Brussels exhibit, 1957 (Box 10)
    - Bush Sabbatical Program, University of Minnesota, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Canadian econometric study group, 1986-1987 (Box 10)
    - Chipman's sabbatical leave, Stanford, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
    - Chipman's 65th Birthday Conference, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Dogmenhistorische Ausschuss, 2001-2002 (Box 10)
    - Early appointments, 1950s-1960s (Box 10)
      Chipman's file of selected letters from various important economists, graduate programs, fellowships, and other notable accomplishments in his early career.
    - Econometric Society: Buenos Aires conference, 1980 July (Box 10)
    - German Marshall Fund, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Global Disequilibrium conference, Montreal, 1989 (Box 10)
      Conference and galley proofs of Chipman's paper
    - Graz honorary degree, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1979-1993; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Humbolt award, 2003 (Box 10)
    - Hurwicz memorial, 2009 (Box 10)
    - IIASA (Vienna), 1978 (Box 10)
    - IMS East Regional workshop, 1979-1981 (Box 10)
    - Indian Statistical Institute, 1974; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Calcutta conference, Mahalanobis Medal committee
    - International Statistical Institute, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Kobe conference on globalization, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Minnesota workshop on Macro theory, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Moscow: Econometrics and international, 1994 (Box 10)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1981-1999; 10 folders (Box 10)
      Membership, meetings
    - National Science Foundation: International Trade project, 1980-1982; 8 folders (Box 10)
      Applications, reports, budget
    - Nemmers Prize, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Nobel Memorial Prize, 1980s-2003; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Pareto seminar, Milan, 2006 (Box 11)
    - Pareto workshop, Italy, 2009 (Box 11)
      Correspondence with Ivan Moscati and Aldo Montesano
    - Phi Beta Kappa induction, 1950 (Box 11)
    - Riksbankens Jubileumsford Ansokan, 1983 (Box 11)
    - Rome Congress of Econometric Society, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Universitat of Konstanz honorary degree, 1991 (Box 11)
    - Vienna Institute for Advanced Studies, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Vienna trip, 1976 (Box 11)
    - Wurzburg honorary degree, 1998 (Box 11)